welcome to the second video on this
series where we are becoming blockchain
developers before we start make sure you
watch our previous video that we did on
this series to understand all the
concepts and the fundamentals required
for blockchain development because
today's video is all about practice what
we're going to do today is we're going
to write a smart contract for a
fundraising application like what is or
kickstarter using solidity a very easy
to use and learn smart contract
programming language and using all that
note which are the sponsors of this
video we are going to learn how to
deploy our code to multiple chains in
record time as always please remember
that if i mention any project on this
video i am doing so for educational
purposes only now let's get started
writing our first smart contract as we
said on the previous video you can write
your smart contracts in a variety of
languages the one that is the most used
and the one that i believe has the
biggest community out there is solidity
solidity is a programming language
influenced by c plus plus javascript and
python that means that it has c plus
plus like syntax which means that if you
know typescript javascript c-sharp java
you're going to feel right at home a
smart contract sounds very scary but
actually it's just a class like a class
that you would find in java or c-sharp
or typescript or javascript or even
python smart contracts have a
constructor they have properties and
they have methods this means that if you
know oop you're going to fly when
learning solidity to create a smart
contract inside of a file called
fundraising.sol
that's all being the extension for
solidity files we are going to write
this line of code at the start of our
file here we are locking the version of
the compiler to make sure that our code
is not compiled by a compiler with a
higher version number and maybe breaking
changes we do this because solidity
changes fast and things break often now
we're going to create a smart contract
called fundraising by creating a class
called fundraising except that instead
of using the keyword class we're going
to use the keyword contract our
fundraising contract is going to have
properties like the owner of the project
which is the person that is trying to
raise money a target amount which is the
money that they're trying to collect a
list of all the people that donated to
the project and how much their donation
was the accumulated amount of total
donations and finally a deadline the
amount of time the project has to reach
the target if the project is over and
the total amount of donations is more or
equals than the target amount then the
money collected is going to be
transferred to the owner of the project
but if the campaign is over and the
amount of donations is less than the
target amount then the people that
donated to the project are going to be
able to get a full refund so let's write
these properties into code by first
specifying the type of the property then
if it's public or private then the name
and optionally an initial value we start
with the target amount this will be an
unsigned integer which means a
non-negative number with a size of 256
bits which is a size that can hold a
number as big as
this then we're going to add a property
called owner it's also public and the
type is of type address which looks like
a string but it has the correct format
to be an ethereum address so we can send
money to it this is the address of the
wallet of the owner of the project where
all the funds will go if the campaign is
successful now we're going to create a
public mapping of the addresses and the
amounts of the people that donated to
the campaign and we will call this
donation you can imagine a mapping like
a hash table or a dictionary where the
key is the address of the person that
donated and the value is how much money
they donated it could look something
like this
now we're going to add the total amount
of the campaign has raised and we're
going to initialize it to zero and
finally we're going to add a finish time
property that would hold the date in
seconds when the campaign will end here
as you can see we're using a variable
called block which is an object that we
didn't define before block will be
defined by the evm the ethereum virtual
machine when we deploy our contract it
will contain the information of the
block that is uploading our contract to
the network blocks have a time stamped
which is the date when they were created
in seconds so we are taking that date
and we are adding two weeks to it this
means our campaign will last two weeks
the weak unit is also provided for us by
the evm next up we will define the
constructure of our class or contract
inside of the constructor is where we
will initialize the target amount and
the owner of the contract properties
that haven't been initialized yet the
constructor will take one argument it is
a number and it will be called
underscore target amount we will then
set the target amount property of our
class to be equals to the underscore
target amount this means we will allow
the owner of the project to specify how
much money their campaign wants to
collect when the contract is being
deployed now to set the owner of our
contract we just have to add this line
of code now this msg or message object
is very similar to the block object that
we used before we did not define them at
all but they will be defined when our
code runs inside of the evm in this case
msg.sender or message sender will be the
address of the actor that is creating
the contract and we are done with the
constructure and the properties as you
can see so far is very easy to
understand now we're going to move on to
the methods of our contract we have to
remember from the previous video that
the evm compatible blockchains have two
kinds of accounts one is an externally
owned account eoa or human account and
the other one is a contract account
which is controlled by code now eoas aka
humans can send money to contract
accounts and also contract accounts can
transfer money to eos because we want
humans to be able to send code to the
contract account and we also want to run
some code when that happens because we
have to increase the counter of how much
money we have and we also have to write
down the address and the donation in our
donation list so we can maybe issue a
refund later we are going to write a
function called received and we have to
say that this function is external which
means it can only be called from outside
of the contract and we will finally add
the payable modifier to it to indicate
that this function can receive money and
that's it now when somebody sends money
to our contract the receive function
will run in the receive function we are
first going to check if our campaign is
not over yet for this we will use the
required function this is a function
that checks if a condition is true and
if it isn't it will throw an error with
a message and it will stop the execution
of our code so in the received function
we're going to say that we require the
block timestamp which is a date to be
smaller than the finished date of our
contract if the block timestamp is of a
bigger value that means that the current
date when this code is being called is
after the finishing date of our contract
if that's true we will show an error
saying that this campaign is over as you
can see here we are using the block
global variable again but inside of the
receive function the block that
timestamp will be the date of the blog
that is being used to save the
transaction created when a user sends
money to our contract if a human is
sending money to our contract and the
campaign isn't over we are going to add
the address of the human that is sending
us the money and the amount of money
being sent to our donations mapping we
are also going to increase the raised
amount counter again we are using the
global variable msg and a property
sender to know who is sending money to
the contract and you are using msg.value
to know how much money they are sending
to the contract we then save this info
in our mapping with the sender as the
key and the amount of money as the value
and we're doing plus equals instead of
equals because people can donate more
than one time if they want to next up
let's write the function to release the
funds to the owner of the campaign if
the campaign is successful for this
let's create a function called we draw
donations withdraw donations we'll check
if the person that is calling this
function is the same person that created
the contract by checking the message
that sender with the owner that we
defined on the constructor before if
they are not the same it will throw an
error and for this we also use require
now we have to check if the raised
amount is more than or equals to the
target of the campaign and if it isn't
we're going to throw an error using
require again the last check of this
function is to see if the campaign is
not over yet if it isn't over we won't
allow the withdrawal to happen if all
these conditions are true if the person
calling the withdrawal donations
function is the owner of the contract if
the raised amount is more than or equals
than the target amount and if the
campaign has finished we will release
the fund to the owner of the contract
we'll do this by calling the payable
function with the address of the owner
that we set in our constructor and then
we call the transfer function to
transfer the value of the raised amount
variable that is keeping track of how
much money has been sent to our
contract now we need to write a function
to give a refund to the people that
donated to our campaign if the campaign
is over and if the campaign didn't reach
the target amount and using require
again we will check if the campaign
reached its goal if it did then there
won't be a refund as well and finally we
will check if the user asking for a
refund is on the donations list if all
these conditions are true if the
campaign is over and if it didn't reach
the goal and if the user that is asking
for the refund did donate to the
campaign we will put the amount of money
that the user donated inside of a
variable then we will update our
donations list to make sure that the
same user cannot ask for a refund twice
and finally we will transfer the donated
money to the user giving them a full
refund and we are done now it's time to
deploy our contract for this video we
are going to use hard hat which as you
will see is very easy to use after we
run npm init inside of an empty folder
we are going to run this command to
install all the things that we need to
install then we will run mpx hardhat to
create a project and we will select the
option to create an empty hardhat config
js we will open
hardhat.config.js and we'll make sure
that the solidity version is the same as
the one in the pragma of our contract if
it isn't we will make the match and we
will also import all the things that we
need for later then we will create a
folder called contracts and there we
will put the fundraising that sold smart
contract that we wrote before now we
need to create an account on the
blockchain this is to be able to deploy
our contract but also to be able to
receive the donations to our wallet for
this we will install the metamask
extension in our browser because
deploying a contract to the ethereum
network costs real money we are going to
instead deploy our contract in a test
network where we can use test money to
pay for our test transactions on this
test network the cryptocurrency ether
has no value even though it has no value
in the test net we still have to get
some for this we're going to go to the
all that node faucet which is a service
where all that node will send you test
money to your test wallet after we go to
the ethereum faucet we will select the
gowerly network which is the test net we
are going to deploy our contract and we
will paste the wallet of the address
that we created in metamask after a
couple of minutes we can go back to
metamask and after selecting the gorly
network we can see that our testimony
has arrived to deploy our contract we of
course have to talk to the ethereum
network and for this we're going to use
all that node so we don't have to
download anything and instead we can
just use their api after we log into all
that node in our dashboard we will
create a new project and select the
ethereum network after the project is
created we will see multiple rpc urls we
will copy the go early rpc url we will
head back to our hardhat config.js and
we will modify our code a little bit to
tell hardhat that we want to talk to
girly by putting this code on the file
as you remember thanks to the awesome
people of all that note we received
testimony in our test wallet and we saw
that in metamask this means metamask is
the only one that is currently
controlling that wallet what i want to
do now is i want to allow hard hat to
control that wallet as well to allow
hard hat to control that account we're
going to go back to metamask and we will
click on account details and then we
will click on export private key this
will show you a key that can be used to
completely control your account you
should not show this to anyone and you
should not upload this key to github for
this tutorial we're going to copy paste
it right into the code but in real life
you should use at that emv environment
file inside of the girly object we will
copy paste our private key inside of an
account array now we are finally done
the setup is complete and we can finally
write the code to deploy our contract
inside of a folder called script let's
create a file called deploy.js and put
this code in there it's pretty easy to
understand what's going on here so let's
go through that using ethers which is a
javascript library to interact with
ethereum we are grabbing the fundraising
contract we are compiling that contract
and then we are deploying it with one
argument this is the argument that the
constructor in our contract needs as you
remember that argument is the target
amount of money that we want to raise in
our campaign as you can also see that
argument is a pretty big number and this
is because just like one dollar is
divided in a hundred cents one bitcoin
is divided in 100 million satoshis and
one ether is divided in one quintillion
way so that number is weight that's the
unit in those ways equal to 100 ether
which is the amount of money that i want
my campaign to receive so if i want to
raise 100 ether for my fundraising
campaign i need to create my contract
with that value onway which is this
number right here we can of course use
ethers to help us format this number now
the last thing that we're doing on this
code is that after our contract is
deployed we are console logging the
address of the contract on the
blockchain so we can go and check it out
on the blockchain explorer to deploy our
contract we're finally going to run this
command right here and if everything
goes well we will see the address of our
contract in our console now all we have
to do is go to the blockchain explorer
of the governly testnet and search for
the address of our contract as we will
see it will show up there which means
our contract is deployed and if we click
on the contract tab we will see our
contract code compiled to bytecode the
bytecode is what the evm will execute
and that's it our contract is live the
campaign is running now let's put some
money in our contract let's donate to
this campaign because the contract as
you can see is just an account with an
address like a human account we can just
send money to it with our wallet let's
copy the address of our contract go to
metamask and send some money to it
as you will see the contract received
some money you can see in the blockchain
explorer the contract has a balance and
that balance increased now let's see if
our receive function actually ran when
the contract received money for this
we're going to interact with our
contract via javascript so let's create
a new task in the hearthout.config.js
inside of that task we will get our
account and we will also paste the
address of our contract now the last
thing we need to be able to interact
with this contract using javascript is
something called the abi it is very
similar to api that we use to
communicate with a server in this case
we use the api to communicate with the
binary contract to get the api of our
contract we will go to the artifacts
folder and then contracts and then we
will find
fundraising.json there we will see the
api and as you can see it's just a json
description of our contract the
functions the return values and the
argument types we will copy paste this
api into our task in the
hearthout.config.js
and now we are ready to interact with
our contract all we have to do is send
the address of the contract the api and
the account of the human that wants to
interact with it and now we can call any
method in our contract using javascript
for example we can check what is the
target amount of our contract and we can
also check to see how much it has been
donated so far to execute this task all
we have to do is run this command in our
console and if it works we're going to
see the target amount of this contract
and also the amount that the contract
currently has and that's it we are done
we did it now if you wanted to deploy
this smart contract to another evm
blockchain like polygon or avalanche all
we have to do is create a new project on
the all that node dashboard to get a
free api key then get test money from
the all that node faucet and add the
network url to our hard hat
configuration file thank you to all the
nodes for sponsoring this video and
thank you for watching it please let me
know in the comments if you would like
me to keep making blockchain development
tutorials like maybe for example adding
a front end to this application using
react or maybe cloning our own
decentralized exchange or nfd
marketplace thank you so much for
watching this video let me know in the
comments what do you think of this video
do you have any questions i'm gonna be
looking at them right now as always stay
free stay happy eat kimchi ham samida
salahyo see you on the next one bye